Xavier University inactive committees records
Xavier University Archives and Special Collections
- Planning Steering Committee All Committee Reports: Integration of the Strategic Plan (Draft), 2003 June (Box 2, Folder 22)
  "In March, 2002, President Graham established the Planning Steering Committee, chaired by Dr. Ronald Slepitza... The committee involved 23 members of the faculty, administration, staff and student body.... Under Slepitza's direction, a whole set of task forces...launched out in several directions... The groups included the Library Planning Committee, Teaching, Learning and Technology Committee, Career Development and Lifelong Learning Committee and 7 others. Over time a smaller work group weaved together the various individual reports into a more coherent whole." (Fortin's history of Xavier, pages 380-381) The committee was charged with "the responsibility of overseeing the university's multiple activities... with respect to planning". (Fortin, page 380) Each of the committee's task forces had its own specific charge which can be found in the final report of each task force.
- Planning Steering Committee All Committee Reports, 2003 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  This folder contains the document "All Committee Reports" dated June, 2003.
- Public Relations Committee, 1940-1948 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  It is unclear when this committee was created and when it was discontinued. It was in existence during the 1940s, though it may not have met during the years of the Second World War. It is sometimes referred to as the "Committee on Public Relations", other times as the "Public Relations Council", and more often as "The Public Relations Committee". The purpose of the committee is not altogether clear from its minutes. The catalogues of the period do not explain its charge. In a general way, it tried to promote the university by advertising it, working to increase its enrollment and raise money among other things.
- Publications Committee, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  According to the annual lists of standing committees, the Publications Committee was created at the beginning of the 1968-69 academic year and continued to exist until approximately 1998, although its name and mandate changed several times. In 1972-73, it became the Programs and Publications Committee. In 1982-83 the name was changed to the Student Programs and Publications Committee. In 1985-86 the name became the Student Publications Committee. It disappeared from the list of committees around 1998. CHARGE OF THE COMMITTEE: In 1972 its charge was as follows. "The committee regularly reviews University publications and makes recommendation regarding general policy as well as evaluations of particular issues. Its student members are nominated by the Student Senate." (Taken from the annual list of standing committees, 1972-73) In 1973 its charge was: "The duties of the committee include the review and interpretation of University policy in reference to student publications and programs, and the review of applications for editors-in-chief of all student publications." (From the annual list of standing committees, 1973-74) In 1992 its charge was: "The Committee works with the editors of the Xavier Newswire and Musketeer Annual to develop editorial policy, to provide regular feedback on content of publications and to select the editor-in-chief of each publication." (From the annual committee list, 1992-93."
- Committee on Research and Advanced Study, 1952-1964 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  It is not known when this committee was created. It was in existence in 1958 with Dr. Harvey A. Dube as its chair. The last memo pertaining to its business is dated 1964. It seems to have been discontinued sometime shortly thereafter. The following is taken from a statement dated January, 1960, entitled RESEARCH POLICIES AND PROCEDURES. "The Committee on Research and Advanced Study (CRAS) of Xavier University is commissioned to develop the basic items of a program for research and advanced study. These items include: 1. Provision for in-service research. 2. Provision for leave of absence to engage in research and advanced study. 3. Inquiry into and adoption of various measures to encourage faculty members to engage in research and advanced study. 4. Provision for University use of this research and advanced study for the purpose of stimulating further scholarly activity."
- Schedule Committee, 1964-1966 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  The Schedule Committee was an ad hoc committee created in the spring of 1964 by the Academic Council. It met for the first time on June 29, 1964. Russell J. Walker served as chair. The last papers pertaining to the committee are dated 1966. The Academic Council probably discontinued it shortly thereafter. The committee's mandate was to devise a new system for the scheduling of undergraduate classes. Such questions as the times and days of classes and the number of classes that would be needed were discussed. The committee also raised a number of questions about the University's academic calendar.
- Speakers and Programs Committee, 1961; 1969 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  According to the annual lists of university committees the Speakers and Programs Committee came into existence at the beginning of the 1968-69 Academic Year. It disappeared from the annual lists at the end of the 1971-72 year. There was a Programs and Publications Committee from 1972 to 1998, but whether this committee replaced or assumed the responsibilities of the Speakers and Programs Committee is not clear. The charge of the committee as of 1971-72 was the following: "Reporting to the Vice President for Student Affairs, the Speakers Program Committee develops general policy recommendations concerning speakers on campus and, upon request from the Vice President, makes recommendations concerning individual speakers and particular programs being considered to appear on campus." (See XU Committee Descriptions, 1971-72)
- ROTC Subcommittee of the Academic Council, 1968-1970 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  The Academic Council, which became the Board of Undergraduate Studies in the fall of 1972, created an ad hoc subcommittee in 1968 to review and make recommendations concerning the future of the university's ROTC program. The committee submitted its final report to the Council on February 7, 1969 and, then, went out of existence. "This subcommittee was established by the Academic Council for the purpose of assembling relevant data for use in the formulation of decisions affecting the future status of the ROTC program at Xavier University.... The fundamental alternatives to consider are whether to drop the ROTC program from the curriculum or to retain a ROTC program in some form on the XU campus." (Final report of the subcommittee, page 1)
- Committee on the Statutes (of the University), 1954-1955 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  The president of Xavier, James F. Maguire, S.J., announced the creation of this committee in a memo to Paul L. O'Connor, S. J., the chair of the committee. The memo was dated August 19, 1954. The committee met through much of the 1954-55 academic year. Its final report, a revised version of the University's statutes, was published on June 1, 1955. The committee was created to revise the Xavier University statutes "as quickly as possible".
- Committee for the Study of Academic and Social Life at Xavier, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  Sometime in 1970 this committee, made up of 5 members of the faculty in the department of psychology and chaired by Vytautas J. Bieliauskas, was created to study the academic and social life on the Xavier campus. It is not clear who established the committee or to whom the final report was submitted. All aspects of campus life from academic standards, faculty and library to student government and intervisitation were examined. The principal instrument employed by the committee was a questionnaire that was developed, distributed and analyzed by the committee. The committee was asked to investigate all aspects of student life on the XU campus and to access the students' attitudes toward campus life. It was also asked to make recommendations for the future.
- Committee on Tuition, 1968-1969 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  This committee was created by President Paul O'Connor, S. J., in November, 1968. It was apparently an ad hoc committee which was never listed among the standing committees of the University and which seems to have gone out of existence at the end of the 1968-69 academic year. Its chair was Victor B. Nieporte, S. J. Fr. O'Connor spelled out the charge of this committee in the following way: "I would like the above named to form a committee to study the question of a possible tuition increase for September, 1969.... The study is to be made as part of our Long Range Plan Study which is now underway. Consequently, your study might also include recommendations for tuition increases during the next five years." (Memo of President O'Connor dated November 15, 1968)
- Committee on University Institutional Purposes, 1945-1946 (Box 3, Folder 33)
  This committee was apparently established by the Academic Council in 1945. It is not known when it ceased to function. The committee submitted a report to the Academic Council dated December 13, 1946. Whether this was its final report is not clear. This committee was apparently set up ty the Academic Council to investigate whether the "curricular departments' were functioning according to the provisions of the University statutes and, if not, what changes should be made.